许多机器和机器人都有多个运动轴。
Many machines and robots have got multiple axis of motion.
工业机器人通常具有六个关节，并且它们必须平稳且协调地移动
An industrial robot typically has six joints and they have to move smoothly and in a coordinated
时尚。
fashion.
我们可以用来帮助我们的技术是线性插值。
A technique we can use to help us is linear interpolation.
考虑这个简单的函数，其中s的x是初始值的函数
Consider this simple function here where x of s is a function of an initial value of
x和最终值x。
x and a final value of x.
并且，s从0到1不等。
And, s varies from 0 to 1.
在这种情况下，那么s的x是某种中间值。
In this case, then, x of s is some sort of intermediate value.
X为0是初始值，x为1为最终值，x为0.5为中间值
X of 0 is the initial value, x of 1 is the final value, and x of 0.5 is halfway in between
初始值和最终值。
the initial and final value.
现在，x可以是一个使多维情况非常简单的向量。
Now, x could be a vector which makes the multi-dimensional case quite straightforward.
例如，它可能是某种机器或简单机器人的xyz位置。
For instance, it could be the xyz position of some sort of machine or simple robot.
因此，x是具有三个元素xyz的向量，我们可以在它们之间线性插值
So, x is a vector with the three elements xyz and we can interpolate linearly between
初始位置，初始xyz和最终xyz。
an initial position, an initial xyz and a final xyz.
S是一个从0到1变化的标量。
S is a scalar which varies from 0 to 1.
那么，什么是s？
So, what is s?
嗯，S是一个从0到1平滑变化的标量。
Well, S is a scalar that varies smoothly from 0 to 1.
并且，如果S是时间的平滑函数，则x将是时间的平滑函数
And, if S is a smooth function of time, then x will be a smooth function of time since
x只是S的线性函数。我们已经知道如何使函数平滑变化
x is simply a linear function of S. We already know how to make a smoothly varying function
时间
of time.
它可以是时间的多项式函数，也可以是梯形速度分布
It can be a polynomial function of time or it could be a trapezoidal velocity profile
时间的功能。
function of time.
我们来看一个二维的例子。
Let’s look at a two-dimensional example.
我们想要在xy平面上移动，我有一个起点和终点。
We want to move in the xy plane and I’ve got a starting point and an ending point.
现在，我想从头到尾直线前进。
Now, I want to move in a straight line from the start to the end.
我将为开始和结束分配一些任意坐标。
I’m going to assign some arbitrary coordinates to the start and the end.
我们回到MATLAB中，现在我们的第一点是矢量，而不是标量。
We’re back in MATLAB and now our first point is a vector, not a scalar.
所以，第一个点是坐标10,20，我们的最后一个点是矢量30,10。
So, the first point is the coordinate 10, 20, and our last point is a vector 30, 10.
而这次，我将使用函数jtraj，代表联合插值轨迹。
And this time, I’m going to use the function jtraj, stands for joint interpolated trajectory.
我将在50个时间步骤中从第一点移动到最后一点，我们看到了
I’m going to move from the first point to the last point in 50 time steps, and we see
一切都滚过去了。
it all scrolling past.
如果我们向后滚动，我们会看到第一个点确实得到了矢量值10和
If we scroll back, we see that the first point has indeed got the vector value of 10 and
20，最后一个点的值为30和10。
20, and the last point has got the value of 30 and 10.
让我们将x绘制为时间的函数，我们可以看到我们的第一个轴已移动
Let’s plot x as a function of time and we can see here that our first axis has moved
从10到30，第二轴从20下降到10。
from 10 up to 30, second axis has moved from 20 down to 10.
此功能也返回速度。
This function also returns the velocity.
所以，我可以添加它作为额外的输出参数，XD。
So, I can add that as an extra output argument, XD.
现在，我们也看到x速度，我可以绘制XD与时间的关系，我们可以看到
And now, we see x velocity as well and I can plot XD versus time, and we can see that the
每个轴的速度从0开始和结束，并且在它们之间具有有限值。
velocity of each axis starts and ends at 0 and has a finite value in between.
该功能还允许我指定轨迹的初始和最终速度。
The function also allows me to specify an initial and final velocity for the trajectory.
所以，如果我要求初始速度为0，这是默认条件，如果我问
So, if I ask for the initial velocity to be 0 which is the default condition, if I ask
最终速度等于10。
for the final velocity to be equal to 10.
现在，如果我绘制轨迹与时间的关系，我们可以看到在轨迹的最后，
Now, if I plot the trajectory versus time, we can see that at the end of a trajectory,
一条线的斜率不等于0，那是因为它正在实现其目的地
the slopes of a line are not equal to 0 and that’s because it is achieving its destination
按我们的指定以有限的速度定位。
position at a finite velocity as we specified.
让我们考虑一个更复杂的二维示例。
Let’s consider a more complex two-dimensional example.
我将在XY平面的这一点开始和结束。
I’m going to start and end at this point in the XY plane.
我要转到这一点，这一点，这一点，回到我开始的地方。
I’m going to move to this point, this point, this point, and back to where I started from.
所以，现在有三个通过点。
So, there are now three via points.
我可以为它们分配一些任意坐标。
I can assign some arbitrary coordinates to these.
为了顺利通过过孔点，我们需要引入混合物和我们
In order to move smoothly through the via points, we need to introduce blends and we
在上一节中谈到了混合。
talked about blends in a previous section.
在这里，我们想要应用这种混合的概念，在这个例子中，它是为标量显示的
Here, we want to apply this idea of blends which, in this example, is shown for a scalar
变量x。
variable x.
我们想将它应用于多维案例，因为现在我们谈论的是一个机器人
We want to apply it to a multi-dimensional case because now we’re talking about a robot
在xy平面上移动。
moving in the xy plane.
所以现在，每个位置XI都是向量而不是标量。
So now, each of the positions XI is a vector rather than a scalar.
现在，我们将看一下轨迹上的点是矢量的情况，
Now, we’re going to look at a scenario where points on the trajectory are vector quantities,
在这种情况下，两个向量，我们有通过点。
two-vector in this case, and we have via points.
让我们在MATLAB中做这个方形轨迹。
Let’s do this square trajectory in MATLAB.
我们的起始坐标是40,50，并且通孔点是60,30，这是一行的
Our starting coordinate is 40, 50 and the via points are 60, 30 which is one row of
矩阵，40,10是矩阵的另一行，20,30，我们在那里完成
the matrix, 40, 10 which is another row of the matrix, 20, 30 and we finish where we
开始。
started.
而且，那是通过点的列表。
And, that’s the list of via points.
现在，我使用工具箱函数mstraj。
Now, I use the Toolbox function, mstraj.
我传入了via点列表。
I pass in the list of via points.
通过我们将沿着路径移动的速度，段的时间
Passing the speed at which we’re going to move along the path, the time of the segments
是默认的。
is default.
现在，开始坐标。
Now, start coordinate.
时间步长，0.1秒和加速时间，我将考虑公正
The time step, 0.1 seconds and the acceleration time, which I'm going to consider to be just
1秒。
1 second.
而且，我在工作空间变量x中创建了。
And, I’ve created in the workspace variable x.
它有435行，这意味着轨迹需要435个时间步骤才能执行
It’s got 435 rows, so that means that the trajectory took 435 time steps to execute
每次步数0.1秒。
each time steps 0.1 seconds.
执行时间为43.5秒。
That’s 43.5 second to execute.
我可以绘制x与时间的关系，我们可以看到第一和第二坐标的轨迹
I can plot x versus time and we can see the trajectory of the first and second coordinates
与时间的第一个坐标以蓝色显示。
versus time first coordinate shown in blue.
如果我将第一个坐标绘制在第二个坐标上，那么可以是x
If I plot the first coordinate against the second coordinate, so that could be the x
坐标，可以是y坐标。
coordinate and that could be the y coordinate.
我有这样的情节。
I have a plot like this.
因此，这显示了点在xy平面上的运动，实际上，它具有正方形
So, this shows the motion of the point on the xy plane and, indeed, it has the square
我们正在寻找的配置文件，但由于我们已经指定，它有圆角
profile that we are looking for, but it’s got rounded corners because we have specified
有限的加速时间。
a finite acceleration time.
让我们现在考虑一个额外的难度。
Let’s consider now an extra degree of difficulty.
让我们考虑机器能够在x方向上以每秒2米的速度移动，
Let’s consider that the machine is capable of moving at 2 meters a second in the x direction,
但在y方向上每秒只有1米。
but only 1 meter per second in the y direction.
当我们计算出机器人的轨迹时，我们需要考虑到这一点。
We need to take this in to account when we figure the trajectory for the robot.
再次考虑这个二维示例，这是我们想要的路径
Consider again this two-dimensional example and this is the path that we want from the
从头到尾，这是我们理想的道路。
start to the end, that’s our desired path.
但是如果机器人能够在x方向上比在y方向上移动得更快，
But if the robot is capable of moving more quickly in the x direction than in the y direction,
路径可能看起来像这样。
the path might look something like this.
它将在x方向上非常快速地移动并且在y方向上移动一点点。
It will go very, very quickly in the x direction and also move a little bit in the y direction.
但是，x轴将实现其目标，因此它将停止移动。
But then, the x-axis will have achieved its goal, so it will stop moving.
但是，移动得更慢的y轴必须继续前进，所以我们最终会这样做
But, the y-axis which is moving more slowly has to keep on going, and so we end up with
这条狗腿路径而不是我们想要的路径。
this dogleg path instead of our desired path.
如果我在像平板仿形机这样的东西上切割材料，那么我就是
If I was cutting material on something like a flatbed profiling machine, then I’d be
如果我有这条道路而不是想要的道路，我会感到很沮丧。
rather upset if I had this path rather than the desired one.
因此，为了达到理想的路径，我们需要考虑到速度
So in order to achieve the desired path, we need to take in to account the velocity of
每个轴。
each of the axes.
我们需要计算出最慢的轴到达下一个通过点所需的时间。
We need to work out how long the slowest axis requires to get to the next via point.
然后，我们缩放其他轴的速度，使它们全部同时到达
And then, we scale the velocity of the other axes so that they all arrive at the same time
在通过点，然后他们都再次出发到下一个通过点。
at the via point, and then they all set off again to the next via point.
我们无限期地重复这个过程。
We repeat this process indefinitely.
现在，我们将重复这个轨迹，但这次我们将指定
Now, we’re going to repeat the trajectory, but this time we are going to specify the
轴的速度不同。
velocities of the axis being different.
因此，以前，速度在x和y方向上为每秒2个单位。
So, previously, the velocity was 2 units per second in the x and y direction.
现在，我将指定一个非常慢的x轴，每秒只有1个单位，以及一个快速的y轴。
Now, I’m going to specify a very slow x-axis, only 1 unit per second, and a fast y-axis.
如果我们现在查看工作空间中的轨迹级别，我们会看到它有835行，
If we now look at the trajectory level in our workspace, we see it’s got 835 rows,
0.1秒的时间步，这意味着轨迹现在需要83秒，几乎是两倍。
0.1 second time step, so that means the trajectory now takes 83 seconds, almost twice as long.
并且，这是可以预料的，因为现在，轨迹正在以最慢的速度进行
And, that’s to be expected because, now, the trajectory is being paced by the slowest
轴。
axis.
最慢的轴现在每秒只能移动1个单位。
The slowest axis now can only move at only 1 unit per second.
以前，它是每秒2个单位，所以现在我们受限于一半的轴
Previously, it was 2 units per second, so we are limited now by an axis which is half
原始速度，轨迹大约需要两倍的执行时间。
the original speed, the trajectory has taken roughly twice as long to execute.
我可以绘制x与时间的关系。
I can plot x versus time.
我们可以看到835个时间步长，我可以绘制x与y的关系。
We can see the 835 time steps and I can plot x versus y.